[MUSIC]
[簡介三種推論統計方法]
In this lecture we'll talk about three
different ways in which you can draw
這段影片來簡單談談三種對資料
statistical inferences from your data.
進行統計推論的方法
We can see that there are three
main questions that you can
我們首先來看三種不同解決問題的角度
ask which are all related to
different statistical approaches.
其分別與三種統計推論方法有關
So let's take a look at
each of these in-turn.
讓我們一個一個來談
Now in statistics,
運用統計方法
we'll see that there's basically one
truth that we all try to figure out.
基本上我們期望能發掘那唯一的事實/真理
But the paths toward this truth, there
are many different ways to try to do this.
不過到達事實/真理的途徑有很多條
One useful metaphor that I think can
help you think about these differences
我想用印度教徒的修行法門(瑜珈)，來比喻說明
is if we look at Hinduism.
三種統計推論方法的差別
The Karma yoga, the Jnana yoga,
and the Bhakti yoga.
其中三種法門：業瑜珈(Karma),信瑜珈(Bhakti), 智瑜珈(Jnana)
(英文說明順序有誤，字幕才正確)
Now if you see what the Hinduist
book [UNKNOWN says about this
薄伽梵歌描述三種法門達到功德圓滿的要旨
there's basically a path of action, a path
of devotion and a path of knowledge.
付諸行動、堅定信仰、愛智求真
And I think there's a nice relation
to make between these three paths and
三種修行法門與三種統計推論方法解決問題的角度
three questions that you can
ask if you do statistics.
有巧妙的相似之處
Now, Royall talks about these three
different questions that one might ask.
Royall曾歸納出三種尋求問題解答的觀點
And he differentiates between what
should I do, what should I believe and
他試著分辨問題本質的不同，包括我該做什麼？我該相信什麼？
what's the relative evidence?
以及我有沒有得到互相對比的證據？
And we see that these are three
different statistical approaches
這三種不同尋求問題解答的途徑
that we can use to draw
inferences from data.
將決定不同方式來運用資料進行推論
The first is the path of action.
先談付諸行動之道
The path of action uses rules to
govern our behavior such that,
此法門講究依循規則行事
in the long run, we won't make
a fool out of ourselves too often.
只要依規則行動，我們就不會被愚弄人心的想法迷惑
Now this approach uses p-values and
alpha levels to either make a decision to
付諸行動之道運用p值與顯著水準的規則
reject the null hypothesis, or to accept
the null hypothesis, or if you want
決定拒絕虛無假設，還是接受虛無假設
to remain in doubt about whether
the alternative hypothesis is true or not.
還有保持對立假設是否為真的懷疑
This is a rule to govern our
behavior in the long run.
這個規則一直指引我們運用統計的行為
It's important to keep in mind that
this doesn't tell you anything about one
必須銘記在心的是
這個規則不會告訴你現在正在做的測試
single test that you're performing.
會是什麼樣的結果
So any current test might
be either true or false.
因此任何一次測試結果可能為真也可能為假
We don't know but
what we know is that in the long run,
雖然我們無從得知
不過依照規則多做幾次測試就能掌握到
there's a certain percentage of
the time that will be correct.
有多少次測試結果為真的比例
So this is the main goal
of the path of action.
這也是付諸行動之道的首要目標
Making decisions about what you should do.
決定你該做的事(拒絕或接受虛無假設)
The path of knowledge, the second way,
focuses on likelihoods.
愛智求真之道的修行是靠「似然性」(likelihoods)
And it tries to answer the question
what the likelihood is
此法門講究要找到似然性才能解決問題
of different hypotheses given
the data that you have collected.
不同假設的似然性是根據你所收集到的資料而定
Let's take a look at the situation
where you flip a coin ten times.
我們拿丟一枚硬幣十次為例子
This is an old Dutch
from when I was young.
這裡有十枚我小時候(歐元未發行前的)舊荷蘭硬幣
And we see that there are six heads and four tales.
其中六枚正面朝上
四枚反面朝上
So if you flip this, if you flip a coin
ten times and this is the data that you
如果把這十枚當成你丟一枚硬幣十次的結果
have observed, you can ask yourself
the question, is this coin biased or not?
你覺得這一枚是不是公正的硬幣呢
So what is the likelihood
that this is a fair where
要如何用似然性評斷這次結果
every option comes up 50% of the time?
是出自一枚公正的硬幣(正反面各50%)
Or what's the likelihood
that this is a biased coin?
或者這樣問
這是一枚不公正硬幣的似然性有多大?
Now we can plot the likelihood function
given the data that we have observed.
若把手上的資料放進似然函數(likelihood function)
我們能畫出這樣的圖
Let's take a look at
the likelihood function.
讓我們仔細端詳這道似然函數
So this curves tells us all
the likelihood of different
圖中的曲線是所有似然值(縱軸)
hypotheses given the data that we have.
對應手上資料能支持的假設(橫軸)之集合
Now we've observed six heads,
so you can see that this,
根據手上六枚正面的結果(0.6)
就可知道這結果的似然值(0.25)
according to the likelihood function,
is the most likely possibility, but
也是這道似然函數的最大估計值
we can also calculate the likelihood ratio.
另外我們也可以計算不同似然值的比值(likelihood ratio)
How much more likely is the data
that we have given a fair coin?
若為公正硬幣投出的結果(0.5)
其似然值是多少(0.2)
And we see that this is
not very impressive.
我們會發現兩種結果的似然值很接近
(0.25/0.2 = 1.25)
The likelihood ratio's supposed to be 1,
當兩種假設(0.6 vs 0.5)沒有差別的話
if there's no difference between different
hypothesis, and this is pretty close to 1.
理論上似然值比值會是1
而這個例子裡似然值比值相當接近1(1.25)
Later on in the course, we'll talk about
how you can really calculate these things.
之後的課程我們會學習如何計算
The last option is the path of belief.
最後來談堅定信仰之道
Now we have flipped a coin ten times, and
we saw that it came up heads six times.
同樣是丟一枚硬幣十次，得到其中六次正面朝上的結果
Now if you see this, do you really believe
that the coin in the long run will come up
你相信不管做幾次測試，都會得到這樣的結果嗎？
heads 60% of the time?
都會有 60% 的測試結果是正面朝上嗎？
Now that seems rather unlikely.
應該不會
You have previous beliefs about coins, and
因為你對硬幣有先驗信念(prior belief)
you have a very strong belief
that most coins are fair.
這信念讓你相信大多數硬幣是公正的
So in the long run you might say,
well, I've observed this.
如果真的能做很多次測試，你應該會說
「我會看到好多次公正結果(0.5)」
This one time there were six heads, but
「雖然這次是六枚正面朝上」
I don't really believe that this is what I
will see if I continue flipping the coin.
「除非繼續測試下去，否則我不會真的相信」
I think, still, that 50% probability
of heads is what's going to happen
「我想總會有很多次，正反面朝上的次數相等」
if I do this over and over again.
「只要我可以反覆做同樣的測試」
So you see that in this case, the data
did not really change your prior beliefs.
這樣的想法反映出一次測試結果並不能改變先驗信念
And this path is known
as Bayesian statistics,
這也是貝氏統計的法門
which allows you to express evidence
in terms of the degrees of belief.
根據手上的證據推測信念程度
So how much do you believe
in a certain hypothesis?
那麼，你有多相信你的假設呢?
So these three different paths, the path
of action, the path of devotion, and
我們簡單談了付諸行動之道
堅定信仰之道
the path of knowledge.
以及愛智求真之道
We can sort of make a relationship to
Neyman-Pearson statistics, which is
三大法門對應到統計推論，首先是
「尼曼-皮爾森統計」相當於「付諸行動」
the path of action using alpha levels to
decide between the null hypothesis and
講求運用顯著水準決定要接受虛無假設
the alternate hypothesis.
還是對立假設
Bayesian statistics, where we talk about
the degree of belief in hypothesis.
「堅定信仰」的「貝氏統計」則在計算對假設而生信念程度
And likelihoods which tell us something
about relative evidence between different
「愛智求真」要評估證據支持不同假設的「似然性」
hypothesis.
Now, in the history of statistics, we see
that there's a lot of discussion going on
在漫長的統計史裡，常看到不同法門之間的
between different sides in this debate.
討論與爭辯
And if you want to know how nasty science
can get, then I invite you to take a look
若想見識科學家之間怎麼打筆戰
我建議去找找看
at the discussion in the scientific
literature between this person on
這些大師論文之中的討論，特別是
the left, Jerzey Neyman, and
the person on the right, Ronald Fisher.
尼曼(左)與費雪(右)的論文來看看
Now, Jerzey Neyman is
about the path of action.
尼曼是付諸行動之道的宗師
And Ronald Fisher uses p-values
in a slightly different way.
而費雪則以不同的路數運用p值
P-values as a measure of evidence.
這裡談的p值是證據力的測量值
Now, Ronald Fisher is a genius, one of
the few geniuses that we have in science.
費雪是科學界普遍公認的絕世奇才之一
He's not only a godfather of statistics,
他不只是統計學的教父
he worked a lot on introducing
analysis of variance, for example.
開創許多統計方法，
像是變異數分析
But he's also a very respected
scholar in the field of biology,
他也是生物學界的一代巨擘
where he did groundbreaking work as well.
因為他也為生物學留下許多奠基之作
So this is no doubt a very smart
individual, but there's a lot of debate
有天兩大宗師狹路相逢，他們要爭辯
about the way that he uses p-values
to draw inferences from your data.
如何使用p值對資料進行推論
So if there's a discussion between these
two individuals, you can say, well,
假想你(己知假設檢定)穿越到了這一天
兩人辯論的高潮時刻
the Neyman-Pierson approach to inference
is definitely the best way, the most
你大概會對尼曼說，他的推論方法是最好的
coherent way, to draw inferences from
data using alpha levels and the p-value.
最有邏輯的方法
因為是靠顯著水準與p值直接推論資料
So Neyman would be really happy,
say, haha, after all these years and
尼曼聽罷必會對費雪大笑說
「哈哈，多年之後...」
this intense discussion that we had,
I've won.
「你我爭論的結果，是我贏了」
My way of doing statistics is
the only logical approach to draw
「我的統計推論方法是唯一有邏輯的方式」
statistical inferences.
On the other hand,
Fisher might not be too sad.
但看費雪這一邊，他應該面不改色
He might say, forget it.
他說「你(尼曼)別傻了」
No one knows who you are,
which is in general true.
「就算你的方法被眾人接受，
也不會有人知道你是誰」
I think not a lot of people have heard of
the Neyman-Pearson approach of statistics.
「我相信只有一小撮人知道你和皮爾森的名字」
And he would be pretty happy
that everybody uses p-values in,
費雪反而會很高興地說
「未來人人都會用p值的時代」
well, arguably, not the optimal way,
but at least the way that he proposed.
「雖然大多數人不會用得很好，
但是使用的方式是我首先提出來的」
And, well,
he gets a lot of respect for this.
他說得一點都沒錯，
假設檢定的觀念是費雪先提出來的
You might not know this, but
the F-distribution, the F-value
你也許還不知道，當你做變異數分析時(ANOVA)
that you calculate in an ANOVA, is
actually named after Fisher in his honor.
會遇到的F分配、F值
就是以費雪的首字母(F)命名
All right, so
these two sides are debating, but
再回來看辯論大會
當兩邊爭得面紅耳赤時
now we see that Bayesian statistics
is on the rise in recent years.
貝氏統計正悄悄地登上爭辯的舞台
This is Reverend Thomas Bayes,
or actually probably not.
這位是托馬斯·貝葉斯神父
也可能不是
This is a picture that's
circulating that might be him, but
這張畫像有傳言說是他本人
it's doubtful that it's actually him.
也有傳言說不是
Nevertheless, we'll use it in this course
to illustrate the Bayesian perspective.
不管如何，我們都用他的姓氏稱呼他帶起
的觀點(Bayesian perspective)
And he would say,
gentleman, Quit fighting.
他穿越來到之後會說
「兩位先生，別再爭了」
Who cares about these frequentist
approaches to statistics that you
「誰會在乎你們發展的"次數分配主義"在統計學裡有多重要」
think are important.
Because everybody in the future will
use Bayesian statistics anyway.
「未來是人人使用貝氏統計學的時代」
We can see whether that's true or not.
我們即將見證究竟這時代會不會來臨
And maybe Neyman would respond, well,
但此時尼曼回應他
I don't have a really high prior
that this is really going to happen.
「我對這事可沒有這麼高的先驗信念」
Which of course, is a sly joke,
當然這是尼曼反諷貝氏的笑話
because he's using prior information
to draw an inference in this case.
尼曼用自已的先驗知識推測貝氏的預言
And you see that when there's a discussion
between Bayesian statistics and
一旁的你會以為這突然亂入的貝式統計
frequentist statistics, all of sudden, of
course, these two become perfect friends.
與次數分配主義(尼曼-皮爾森取向)
是好哥兒們
They say, of course, very good joke.
三位大師會認為你的看法是個笑話
And they will be in agreement
about the way to do statistics.
卻也會同意你對統計推論的看法
Now the third approach is
the likelihood approach.
最後我們來看似然性取向
It's not very popular at the moment, but
likelihoods underlay Bayesian statistics.
雖然這方法目前還不流行，但似然性是貝氏統計的基礎
And the difference between likelihoods and
Bayesian statistics,
兩者之間的差異在於
is that likelihoods do use the relative
evidence that's present in the data,
似然性是根據目前資料呈現的相對證據
as Bayesian statisticians do.
正如貝氏統計學家的做法
But it doesn't rely on
this subjective prior.
但是似然性取向的方法不在乎先驗信念
One of the proponents of this
approach is Rich Royall.
Rich Royall是其中一位支持者
And he might say something that nobody
really cares about your subjective opinion
他會說研究者在使用統計推論時
沒人會在乎研究者的主觀想法
when you draw inferences from data.
他會說研究者在使用統計推論時
沒人會在乎研究者的主觀想法
So you should ignore this subjective
prior and only rely on the likelihood.
所以研究者不必管主觀先驗機率
只要靠似然值就行
To which Thomas Bayes might say,
come on, don't be such a nuisance.
但是貝葉斯神父大概會回應他
「別這麼天真」
Nobody even knows what
likelihood paradigm is.
「沒有先驗信念就沒人知道似然函數的樣子」
At this moment this might be true but
we'll see you can use it for
此時也許神父是對的，不過在之後的課程裡
certain useful things later
on in these lectures.
你會學到似然性取向有用處的地方
Now, it's very important to
realize that in this debate,
像這樣的爭論，你該了解到
which sometimes feels a little
bit like Microsoft versus Apple,
有點像微軟與蘋果孰優孰劣之爭
there's always this
clash between two sides.
兩邊總會有爭執
And people will start to argue vehemently
between these two different approaches.
也會吸引人們跳進去參戰
For you, it's very important that you
can use whatever answers your question.
對於這門課的同學
重要的是了解該用什麼角度解決問題
And that's really the main point.
才是學習這門課程的重點
It's not either, or.
不是只能使用一種方法，而是
You can even combine these
approaches if you want to.
你可以融合兩種甚至三種取向
So the important take-home message here is
that there are three different approaches
我要給各位的記憶重點是透過參與這門課程學習
in how you can draw
inferences from your data.
三種從資料進行統計推論的方法
These all answer a question
you might be interested in.
三種方法都能回答你有興趣的問題
And the main thing is that you
realize that there are all
一旦你掌握了所有統計推論的方法
these different approaches, so
you can ask the question that will
give you the answer that you want.
你便可以正確問出那條你真正想得到答案的問題
[影片結束]